Finding Aid of the UW-Milwaukee Employment and Training Institute, 1976-2015
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
UW-Milwaukee Employment and Training Institute, 1976-2015
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. Employment and Training Institute
UWM Archival Collection 230
2 cubic ft. (2 boxes)
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
Records of the Employment and Training Institute (ETI), a research center in the School of Continuing Education which addresses the needs of unemployed and underemployed Wisconsin workers and families. The collection is comprised of education and employment publications on GED assessments, post-secondary education and employment for GED and Milwaukee Public School (MPS) graduates, and the labor market and AFDC single-parent employment in Milwaukee. Also included in the collection are job opening and job seeker surveys and news clippings on MPS desegregation and national and local race, labor, and education issues.
The Employment and Training Institute (ETI) was established in 1978 by the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee and the University of Wisconsin-Extension to address the educational and training needs of unemployed and underemployed Wisconsin workers and families. ETI was established as part of UW-Extension's implementation of the "Wisconsin Idea", which indicates university research should be applied to solve problems and improve the quality of life for all Wisconsin citizens. ETI addressed the educational and employment needs of youth and adults through research and community education.
Directors of ETI
1978-1988 Philip E. Lerman
1988- John Pawasarat
The majority of the collection contains research and training publications produced between 1980 and 2003. Publications include GED and MPS graduate employment and post-secondary education readiness, juvenile ex-offender and youth employment, Metropolitian Milwaukee job opening surveys, and Milwaukee County educational and employment guide and single parent AFDC population and employment earnings. The collection also contains local news clippings from 1976 on MPS desegregation, and national and local news clippings on racism, neighborhood segregation, youth and adult employment, GED assessments, youth education, and welfare reform.
The collection is organized into three series:
Publication Files, 1980-2015
News Clippings, 1976-2003
Web Archives, 1980-2015
The files are organized alphabetically by subject, then chronologically.
Related Material in the UWM Libraries
UW-Milwaukee Center for Urban Community Development Records UWM Archival Collection 223
UW-Milwaukee Milwaukee Urban Observatory Records UWM Archival Collection 73
UW-Milwaukee School of Continuing Education Records UWM Archival Collection 176
Administrative/Restriction Information
The records in the Web Archives Series were collected using the Archive-It Web Archiving tool.
There are no access restrictions on the materials, and the collection is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
The Employment and Training Institute Collection was transferred to the Archives by Lois Quinn as part of accession 2016-036 in February 2017.
Deaccession Information
One box of publications received as part of accession 2016-036 was removed from the collection and added to the Milwaukee Urban Observatory Collection (UWM Archival Collection 73).
Contents List
- Records, 1976-2015, UWM Archival Collection 230; 2 cubic ft. (2 boxes)
  - 1. Publication Files, 1976-2015
    - Acceptance of GED Holders at Post-Secondary Institutions in Wisconsin, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Basic Education for Adults, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Centro Hispano Head Start Community Needs Assessment, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Comprehensive Employment and Training Act and Private Sector Job Creation, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Education for Employment
      - Background Readings, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Consumer Economics Curriculum with Handouts for Poor Readers, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Job Skill Curriculum with Handouts for Poor Readers, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Employer Perspective: Jobs Held by the Milwaukee County AFDC Single Parent Population (January 1996 - March 1997), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Employment and Earnings of Milwaukee County Single Parent AFDC Families: Establishing Benchmarks for Measuring Employment Outcomes Under "W-2", 1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Employment and Education Experiences of Milwaukee Public Schools Graduates: A Follow - Up Study of the Class of 1999, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Equivalency Certificates: Findings and Recommendations, Report to the Superintendent, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - The GED as a Measure of Readiness for Employment, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - A GED Primer: Background Information for Dr. Herbert Grover's GED Work Group, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Head Start Community Assessment Data Analysis, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Interim Report to the Wisconsin Legislature on the Work Experience and Job Training/Community Work Experience Program Evaluation, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Literature Survey of the Use of the GED to Measure Readiness for Post-Secondary Education, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Milwaukee County Labor Market and Employer Directory, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Milwaukee County Planning Guide for Education and Employment, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Model Reentry Programs for Juvenile Ex-Offenders, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Performance of GED Holders Enrolled at UW's Thirteen Campuses: 1979-1985, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Recommendations for Improving Milwaukee County Job Training Partnership Act Programs, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Survey of Central City Milwaukee Job Seekers: Fall 1995, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Survey of Job Openings in the Milwaukee Metropolitan Area
      - Week of May 23, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Week of October 24, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Week of May 22, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Week of May 15, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Week of October 21, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Week of October 20, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Teenage Undereducation and Unemployment: What Approaches Work?, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Vocational Education Project: Summary of Recommendations and Statement of Philosophy, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Wood County Planning Guide for Education and Employment, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Work Assistance Research Project, Final Report, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Youth Employment Competency Tests and Curriculum Guide
      - Community Resources, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Consumer Economics, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Government and Law: Youth Employment Competency Tests and Curriculum Guide, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Health, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Interpersonal Relationships, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Job Skills, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Math, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
      - Reading, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Writing, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 2. News clippings, 1976-2003
    - 1989-2003 (Box 2, Folder 5-12)
    - School Desegregation, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 13-18)
  - 3. Web Archives, 2008-2017, series3; 180 captures
    Home Page of the the Employment and Training Institute, including a majority of their publications from 1976-2016. The links to the Labor Market Drilldowns on the Publications page are active, but do not properly link to the drilldown database; most other publications have been captured.
    Web crawling is managed through the Internet Archive's Archive-It service. This series includes links to both the university's collection and the Internet Archive's public collection.
    Web records from UWM are collected on a semi-annual basis. Crawls of the UWM Web Site may be performed at more frequent intervals in cases of major events, significant additions or changes to the UWM Website or the websites of schools and colleges, etc. Social Media feeds are crawled on an as-requested basis.
    Web Archives collected by the Internet Archives Wayback Machine and Archive-It Web Harvesting Tools.
    - Archive-It Capture, 2015 August 28-2017 March 22 (Web-archive 1)
    - Internet Archive Capture, 2008 December 5-2017 March 22 (Web-archive 2)